a clean record all right hello everyone
and welcome to handmade hero the show
where we code a complete game live on
Twitch from scratch no engine no
libraries no nothing uh just so we can
learn basically everything that is
involved in the complete sort of uh
software stack of a game all the way
down to the hardware which I think is
actually really important and is uh
becoming a little bit more of a lost
start these days so this project kind of
an attempt to bring that back to
basically have everything there from
start to finish so anyone who wants to
really study uh how games work through
the entire uh pipeline through the
entire code base have the opportunity to
do so and I think it's really great too
just in general for everyone to kind of
be aware of this sort of stuff I know it
certainly makes it much easier for me to
do uh any kind of work that I'm doing on
games whether it it happens to be using
libraries or happens to be using engines
or not because you can always go in
there and fix stuff you can debug so
much more effectively you can know when
something is suspicious uh just when you
have sort of that that kind of um that
kind of full background so that's we're
doing here and we have basically
finished um sort of our prototyping
layer we made a win32 layer uh the past
couple weeks so that we can basically uh
do all of our own stuff right on top of
Windows without having to use any
libraries or anything and it's pretty
basic at this point it does uh basic
sound output and basic uh bitmap output
but and also it does basic um input from
user devices like keyboards uh and
gamepads and that's really everything
that we need to get a game up and
running so that's exactly what we're
going to start doing here but I felt
like we had done a bunch of the hard
work of like picking through windows and
like dealing with all of its apis to do
stuff um and really we were just doing
that in order to get sound output bit
map output and input uh into the thing
and so what I thought would be nice to
do tonight um is to do something fun
with the windows API to kind of show
like okay when you're down there and
you're doing crazy stuff uh you can
actually do some cool things if you've
done all of this yourself and so what I
wanted to show is kind of like an
example of something pretty cool you can
do and it's going to be an example um of
sort of um something very useful to a
game developer so uh if you are
following along at home here on day 21
if you have purchased the source code
using this handyandy pre-order button
here on handmad her.org you will get a
uh Link in your email that um should
have allowed you to basically there's a
link that comes when you pre-order the
game and that will always allow you to
download the source code so save that
link uh go there and there should be a
day20 uh ZIP file inside the source code
ZIP if you unzip that one that is the
source code we're starting with so look
for day20 uh because every day we start
with the previous day source code so if
you unzip that into a directory you will
have exactly the same source code that I
am starting with now so you can follow
along at home which I know a lot of
people like to do so uh let's go ahead
uh in there and um we have some stuff uh
we have a few issues uh that I have in
my notebook that I want to address from
previous days but right now I'm just
going to go ahead and do this we we'll
get to them in the Q&A so I'm going to
go ahead and jump right into like new
stuff uh sort of the fun stuff that I
want to do so all right so basically one
of the things that people often ask me
in fact they asked me this multiple
times uh on the uh sort of about
handmade hero uh they basically say like
are you going to implement a scripting
language this is asked this has been
asked many
times or more specifically I suppose are
you going to use a scripting language
and the answer is no of course we're not
going to use a scripting language uh but
the question whether or not we were
going to build a scripting language well
that would still be making something
from scratch so we could decide to build
our own scripting language if we want to
but we have to ask ourselves the
question is building a scripting
language really all that great I of an
idea right um and in order to know
whether it's a great idea not you have
to kind of stop and ask yourself what do
you think you're going to use this
scripting language for uh and is it
going to provide more benefits to you uh
versus the downsides that a scripting
language has and of course scripting
languages have a lot of downsides that
maybe people don't realize right away
one of uh which is performance problems
because remember if you implement a
scripting language you are also on the
hook for ensuring that that scripting
language is performant which may mean
that you have to use J in time
compilation or all these other sorts of
things in order if you know if a
significant amount of your game is
written in the scripting language uh
you're on the hook for that performance
and that's something you have to be
aware of right it's not like C where you
know how to optimize it and you've
already got tools uh to profile it and
all these and a optimizing compiler
there to back you up it's not like that
when you're using a scripting language
you're on your own right uh and
similarly with scripting languages you
have to ask yourself what are you going
to do about debugging do you have a
debugger for the scripting language are
you going to write one yourself uh are
you going to use some third party one
and will that integrate properly with
the debugger for the platform that
you're using or you going to have to
constantly ping pong back and forth
between debuggers there's all sorts of
things that could go wrong and so when
you're talking about implementing a
scripting language there's a huge number
of costs that go with it and so you have
to be very aware of those costs now that
doesn't necessarily mean that you
shouldn't do it uh but it does mean you
have to think very hard about whether or
not it's a good decision for handmade
hero since we're doing everything from
scratch I think it's kind of a
no-brainer that it would be a bad
decision because we're certainly not
going to want to take the time to write
a debugger for the scripting language
and an Optimizer for the scripting
language compiler from the scripting
language blah blah blah blah blah blah
all the things we would have to do to do
a really good job of using the scripting
language in a game we're not going to do
those things uh because that would take
a huge amount of time out of learning
the stuff we want to learn which is more
about how to write the game code and so
uh given that that's the case uh I would
then say well okay what are the reasons
why people might want a scripting
language like what is a scripting
language good for why or do they even
think they need it uh and can we just go
ahead and get those benefits without
having to do all of the work right so I
think one of the primary benefits of the
scripting language is that people
perceive it to be easier to write things
in a scripting language I don't really
know necessarily where that comes from
so much because I think it's actually
pretty easy to write things than see if
you make the API to it correct uh so I
don't think we're going to have too much
trouble writing our game code in C I
think we're probably going to be fine
with that uh but one of the other things
that people uh often point to in
scripting languages that's a benefit is
the fact that we can do things like edit
the scripting language while the game is
running now this is a pretty big bonus
in a lot of cases because if you can
edit the scripting language while the
game is running you can tune variables
live on the Fly you don't have to try to
you know exit recompile go back into the
game that sort of thing and you can also
do stuff like well if you're trying to
debug the behavior a boss monster you
can just go in there you know get when
you get to the boss monster and see this
not working you can just right there pop
up the script start editing it see what
the boss monster does and change it and
all that stuff and it saves you from
having to make a whole bunch of
scaffolding to allow you to like exit
the game change some boss moner code
jump back into the game jump straight to
the boss monster actually deal with the
um the stuff there look see how it went
go okay it didn't work jump back out
blah blah blah um so there's kind of a
lot of stuff there where it's like that
ability to just use uh to edit the code
um right in the middle of the game is
pretty valuable actually that's a pretty
big thing and so there is something you
can do there right you can inside Dev
studio right if I open up Dev Studio
there's a thing called edit and continue
uh right which allows you to edit stuff
inside Dev Dev Studio you can set a
break point you can edit some stuff and
you can have it recompile uh and that
works for some very limited cases like
unfortunately a lot of the time edit
continue doesn't really work like if
you're writing tons of new functions and
if you're actually trying to really
write new code edit and continue doesn't
work if usually for small changes is the
only thing that it's really reliable for
uh otherwise it mostly just breaks so
editing continue isn't really a good
solution but it's sort of like what we
would want right what we'd like to be
able to do is just kind of go like all
right the game's running and we have the
C code we want to just be able to edit
the C code and have the game just keep
on running right uh so the question is
well could we basically Implement our
own version of edit and continue right
like is there some way uh that we could
go ahead and do that where we actually
don't have to worry you know we we we
basically don't have to care um about
visual C++ and whether it can do
whatever it's supposed to be doing with
its compilation step could we actually
make it uh so that we have what amounts
to our own sort of relatively foolproof
edit and continue uh and so what I'm
going to do tonight is I'm basically
going to try to implement that I'm going
to try to implement a way where we can
basically have our game running change
the code live and not have to restart
the game to see the results uh and just
basically let us kind of go from there
and we'll see how far we can get uh
towards that goal basically
and uh I think that's kind of fun why I
said tonight's kind of time to do
something fun rather than spending all
our time doing stuff just to get Windows
sort of as a conduit working let's see
if we can actually use Windows to help
us now uh to make something pretty cool
so the first thing that I want to do is
go all right well what I know about the
way that I've set up the game because I
think I've architected it pretty well is
basically I've got this sort of platform
independent part here right uh that's
going to hold all of the game code it's
going to hold that stuff that I want to
be able to edit on the Fly and then I've
got a win32 portion which is separate uh
so the first thing that I'm going to
want to do uh is I'm going to say well
could I just split those two things uh
apart so that we basically have uh one
part that's the the platform code that's
compiled separately and one part uh that
is the platform nons code that's
compiled separately and then maybe you
know just merge them together and you
know can I do that in some way that
doesn't uh Force us to unload uh to to
to kill the executable and you've
already basically seen
the answer to this question is yes right
because you've already seen uh that we
have a thing here which is basically uh
the load Library I don't know if you
remember when we were talking about this
uh kind of a while back we have the
ability to load code out of a library
already dynamically right um we can
basically pass a file name uh that's one
of these dll things right that's
something that that Windows has
implemented we can load that in we can
call get proc address on it right and
get proc address will give us a pointer
to a function that's in there and then
we can just call the function right so
if we want to do that we could just do
that with our own code so there's really
no reason why I couldn't instead of
compiling this monolithically as one
translation unit I just compile it as
two separate translation units one for
the platform code one for the platform
independent code right and that platform
independent piece of code I didn't just
load as if it's a dll I call into it to
do whatever it is I needed to do and
then when I want to refresh it if I feel
like it's uh needs to be reloaded I can
just close it I can just Free Library
which is the corresponding call to load
Library I can just free that library and
reload the new freshly compiled code and
I don't have to kill my executable right
I mean it should just work so the reason
that this is simple is because as you
know we're basically passing in the game
memory as a chunk now I've said a couple
times that there's a lot of good reasons
to do this well this is a bit one of
them since we're passing in all of the
game memory the game itself is not imp
the the the actual game code is never
actually doing anything with memory so
if we just keep if we just hold on to
that game memory which we've allocated
we pass it to the dll when it needs to
run we can unload that dll and we still
have all the memory so if we then reload
another dll that's a new version of the
game code we can just call into that and
pass it the same exact memory that the
previous DL was using and poof it'll
just go ahead and keep running in there
now there's a couple caveats of times
when it doesn't uh allow you to do that
because of depending on what you change
in the C++ code uh but for now that's a
pretty easy way to Envision a very
simple way uh to make this work so what
I'm going to do here uh is I'm just
going to change our build.bat a very
very tiny amount right basically instead
of compiling uh this this 64 bit instead
of compiling it uh this way I'm actually
going to compile two different things
I'm going to compile uh the handmade.
CPP I'm going to compile that and I'm
going to compile the win32 hand made.
CPP exactly uh like that so basically
what happens here is inside this where
we have this sort of stuff here right
I'm effectively going to uh start to
bifurcate these two code paths right I'm
going to go ahead and take into handmade
hero. uh I'm going to go ahead and pull
the things that we actually uh had pound
toin out here right I'm going to pull
those into here like this uh so that now
I've basically got oops I should keep
that at the top so now that I've kind of
got those out there this guy is still
going to look uh at handmade. right uh
like this this guy's still going to have
to look at that it's going to need to
see a couple of these things right uh
but uh now it's no longer going to
include uh this handmade. CPP anymore uh
that's not going to happen so instead
handmade. CPP is only going to happen
inside actual handmade. CPP so it's
going to be compiled separately we're
not going to like pound include the CPP
file into win32 handmade right does that
make sense uh so then all I need to do
in my build.bat and there's a couple
other things we're going to have to do
here but but basically all I have to do
in my hand in my handmade here. bat is
figure out uh my build.bat I should say
is I have to figure out what to pass uh
to this CL thing to build one of these
dlls one of those DLS that we were
loading before uh basically the compiler
has the ability to build DLS as as well
as link with them and so on like we were
doing where we're linking with import
libraries and doing stuff like that it
has the ability to build uh DLS itself
so what I really want to do is just make
it so that I can build that dll as as
well uh and so what I have to do there
is I believe it I think it's a pretty
straightforward switch actually I
believe it's just a a a dll switch to
the Linker it's been a long time since I
passed it but I'm pretty sure there's
almost nothing to it it's like yeah it's
just that SL dll uh I believe that's
pretty much almost almost the entirety
of all we're going to have to do so
slash dll there I think is all we're
going to have to do and I don't think
we're really going to have to do
anything else we don't actually even
need need uh most of those other Libs
there as cuz cuz really in fact we don't
really need any of this stuff none of
these common Linker flags are actually
relevant to us I think all we actually
need uh is the SL D so let's go ahead
and take a look at what that does first
just so I can see um what's going on
here all right uh these guys are no
longer internal obviously these are
actual uh linkage calls we'll have to
deal with that in in a second here let's
see here so we got to get rid of that
because they're going to be exported
this is the first time we'll ever have
an exported function let's take a look
we've got uh those are not yes right
these are the calls these are our calls
back uh back into it let's see here do
go platform read entire file uh so these
are no longer internal either those are
going to be like that uh and there we go
all right so now I think uh besides
having our unresolved externals I think
we're in pretty good shape here uh let's
take a look at at our our errors in
win32 handmade as well uh because we
were expecting Linker errors that we're
going to deal with those a second I'll
explain how to deal with those in a
second but I just want to take a look at
these let's see here um we've got right
these are no longer internal these are
called externally um although that's not
really true well we'll see in a second
what we do with those those are probably
premature all right so basically all I
did was I just split the code into two
compilation units and as you can see
there's basically places where they
called each other game update and render
and game set get sound samples and then
the the debug uh read uh free file
memory WR entire file and uh and read
entire file these are basically the
places where are two halves of our code
called each other and so as you can see
now that we're compiling them separately
we just get a bunch of linker errors
that tell us uh you know I can't resolve
this stuff anymore you you're calling
stuff that doesn't exist in the
translation you I don't know where to
find it and that's an error so what we
have to do is figure out ways to resolve
these now the the um two where the
platform L calls the game I just said
how we can do that that's really
straightforward for us to resolve we're
going to treat it just like we treated X
input um where we're going to load
library and do that kind of stuff you
can see here where we basically have um
sort of these get proc addresses this
sort of stuff that's all we really need
to do so really all we need to do here
is uh basically do something where we go
uh win32 load game code or something
like this uh and all we're going to do
with that is we're just going to do that
load library and we'll we'll call this
handmade. dll for for now we can
obviously play with that a little bit
later um handmade code or we just call
this game code uh or game code dll if
that actually works um then we will try
to do get proc addresses on it and those
get proc address calls will give us the
pointers to uh those exported functions
that we wanted so basically we've we're
in here uh you can see we've got game
update and render and game get sound
samples all I'm going to do now is do
the exact same Tri we did for X input
it's going to be literally exactly the
same it's this this exact stuff right
here nothing nothing else to it so all
I'm going to do is basically say uh
there is a
game uh update and render and that takes
a name and it is exactly this function
prototype that we had here before um so
I'm just going to go ahead and make that
like this uh then I will make a type def
for it just like I did before and this
will be called game
update and render and then I will make a
stub for it uh just like I did before so
this will be uh game update oops game
update and render stub and of course
that doesn't need to actually return
anything so that's it uh that's really
all I need to do there and uh we don't
actually even need a global variable for
it I don't think we might do something
slightly different uh than that so I'm
going to I'm going to delete those those
do not need to be there so this is the
entirety
of what we needed to do there and we'll
get rid of that like that okay so we're
going to do that and then the other
thing that we're going to do uh is we're
going to do the same thing for get sound
samples so get sound samples again will
be a game get sound samples and this
will take a name and then we're just
going to use this exact same function
prototype that we were using before for
game get sound samples only now it'll do
this
uh and then I will do a type def of it
did I remember to remove the semicolon
there no I did not doesn't really matter
but I want to get rid but anyway uh just
to be cleaner you can have more than one
semicolon at the end of the line it
doesn't seem that anyone really cares a
lot of the time but just you know just
to keep it a little cleaner so this is
game get sound samples right and then
I'm going to do a game get sound samples
uh oops get sound samples stub samples
St like that uh so that's really about
it uh then what I would like to do uh
because I don't see any reason why not
is I would like to then say well uh
we're going to do so there's a couple
different ways that I could have done
this in fact you know what maybe I'll do
this slightly even a little bit
differently uh instead of having stubs
for these uh since I don't actually
really need this well yeah it's a
little it's it's a tough call it really
is uh but you know what I think I'm
going to I'm think I'm going to do one
more I think I'm just going to go one
more and I'm going to do uh
game uh get uh functions let's say we
call game get functions and basically
game get functions is just going to be
something that basically returns these
functions oh do I need you know what no
I don't I'm only going to have to it it
it I'm conflicted you can hear it in my
voice you know it's true uh but I'm not
I was going to try a different way and I
just wasn't sure I can't quite tell
exactly which one I want uh but I'm
going to stick with the one that I was
originally doing so we're going to do it
that way and that means that inside here
I'm also going to go ahead and say that
game get sound samples uh is actually uh
going to be uh one of these now right so
that's that so that'll automatically
Define that for us and game update and
render is also going to be one of those
so there we go like that and we may have
a little bit of funkiness that we have
to do there as well that'll tell you
about a second but yeah so now hopefully
we can still compile and we can so
that's good uh and now inside here when
I do the load game code remember I'm
still including handmade. just so I can
see these type these defined types here
uh basically what I want to be able to
do now is I want to be able to actually
get proc address uh these things here so
I'm going to try and load uh game get
sound samples I want to load that uh and
that is a game get sound samples pointer
like that uh and that's going to load
from our game code do right so I want to
do that and I'm going to make a little
struct here which is win32 game code and
it's going to have pointers to both of
these things it's going to have pointers
to this that and pointer to this so that
get sound samples and this is game well
actually I don't need the word game
anymore let's get sound stles and this
is update and render and basically what
I'm going to do here is just say that
there's a win 32 game code struct it
comes back from this so we have 132 game
code that's the result and basically
what happens is that right uh we will
initialize to the stub functions equals
the stub there and result uh there's a
stub there uh so
basically get sound samples we will
start off pointing just to St function
so things that don't do anything then
assuming we can actually load it uh we
will go ahead and do it this way so we
can get our uh our functions in here so
get sound samples uh we'll go there and
game update and render uh we'll go there
up date and render like that uh and
there we go okay uh so that's pretty
good and then I will return that result
back okay so now what should be able to
happen uh just to start things off to
get us sort of in POS in Striking
Distance of what we want to do uh at
least in the platform layer stuff I'm
just going to do this sort of at the
outset the first thing I'm going to do
is just do this now we're going to have
to move this later because we want to re
we want to load things on the fly but uh
for now what I'm going to do is just do
this and then um from then on basically
I should have two errors here yeah I can
just do game code or just game update
and render uh and then the get sound
samples right can be game. get sound
samples uh and let's see here so there
we go so now uh our our win32 platform
layer compiles properly um and basically
what it's doing now is instead of
actually calling functions uh that that
are in its own executable so the Linker
resolves them now what it does is it
leaves
um those function calls uh it makes
those function calls go through pointers
and those pointers uh we are loading
inside uh this game code function so
basically anytime we want to we could
always just reload them right we could
go ahead and full on reload them uh and
I also want to set us up for a success
here to the to the extent uh possible by
basically saying uh that the dll itself
will go up here um and so that way we
we'll track basically uh when we load it
so that we can basically free it later
to load a new one right that's so I just
want to track that instead of it having
be having it be entirely local to this
thing so there we go now we've we've got
that stuff and what I want to do here
again is also check to make sure that we
actually got these uh and that they're
not bogus so what I can do is basically
have something in here which is like you
know is valid or something like this uh
and basically I can make is valid be
equal to these two guys um oh in fact
you know what there's another thing I
can do here which is which will be cool
so we'll check to make sure we got both
things uh and if we didn't get both
things uh then it's invalid but what I
can also do there is move this down here
right I can say if it's not valid uh
then set them to the stub function so no
one fails so that's kind of nice and
clean that'll work pretty well uh but
now we we at least can return to whether
or not we actually think we got the
functions that we wanted to get uh so
that seems like it should work okay for
now uh and that will load that handmade.
dll but now we have to deal with the
reverse process right how are we going
to deal with that how are we going to
deal with that because we can't get proc
address back on our executable or maybe
we
could we could load the executable in
the dll load a handle to that and
reverse call into it right we could do
that could do all sorts of fun things
but if you think about it really there's
no need to do that that that would just
be a waste of everyone's time because if
you think about it when we pass in our
structure here um we pass in all these
things when we call game update and
render everybody is getting the game
memory struct for example we could just
decide that inside the game memory
struct we also pass uh the pointers to
the debug Services right we can just
just we can just flat out past those
right because these things here don't
actually have to be function calls they
can just be pointers to function calls
right so we can do the exact same same
thing in the reverse only instead of
having to get proc address them we just
pass them because we already have a
pointer to the game code so when we call
into it we'll just pass it right it's
it's it's it's totally simple it's it's
trivial there's there's no reason not to
do it uh so let's go ahead and do it so
the debug services will just be done the
exact same way um basically we have
debug platform read entire file uh and
that's it for that uh we will type def
that this way right uh we just have to
go ahead and
and oh wait that's not right there we go
debug platform read entire file uh and
that will just take this guy
here okay uh and then the same is true
uh for the rest of these guys debug
platform free file
memory oops that's no good that goes up
in here so that'll basically be the same
thing again
name type def debug platform free file
memory like that and this should be name
as well get those out of there okay the
type deps are good uh and the last one
same thing so basically instead of
actually ever defining the functions in
here uh this is write entire file
instead of actually doing that we're
just going to not do that we're just
going to Define what types they are uh
and assume later that someone will pass
pointers of them to the game right uh so
write entire file there it is so now we
have defined the types for those
pointers and a macro that defines uh
something of that type so that we can uh
use that inside the platform layer and
basically all we need to do now is just
pass these to the game so I'm going to
stick them in game memory for now I'm
just going to say inside game memory uh
you you actually also get basically
pointers uh to to all these things debug
uh oh wait that type those are those are
named wrong those are named wrong that a
typo go back up here this should be
debug platform free file memory and
debug platform write entire file like
that okay so basically all we need to do
is just actually pass pointers to each
of these things with
this right that's it uh and so this will
be uh debug platform read entire file uh
debug platform free file memory
and debug platform right entire file so
we have those now and sort of what we've
done here is basically created our own
little V table if you think about it
it's sort of almost like making our own
little dispatch only instead of it
having to be all C++ and weird we
actually can see it and do whatever we
want with
it so now when we pass game memory we
should just be able to call our stuff
directly out of that uh what did I do I
did something wrong here um
uh Undeclared identifier debug PL oops
that's no good that's no good got to
pass the name there we go uh and then in
these so anywhere where we were calling
those now uh we can just we can just
call them straight off of our memory
right just like that and that's it so uh
basically I think that is basically all
we need to do here uh got to move that
up above there because this actually
calls that that should be it for that
all right so now all we have to do is
actually initialize those in our uh
memory call so these should actually be
uh these guys here should actually be
using this macro because that way if the
macro changes these will be correct so
we've got free file memory and I'll
rearrange the order here I like things
to always be in the same order
everywhere I don't know why but I just
like everything to be in the same order
it's some kind of OCD tendency uh so
anyway uh we'll go ahead and do that so
there we go debug platform free file
memory right entire file will now be
defined with the macro so again this is
just making it so that I don't have the
same uh parameter list in tons of
different places because that just makes
for more maintenance work for me which I
don't want to do uh so there we go and
now if I build this we should be good to
go of course we have never actually uh
when we created our game memory struct
we haven't actually set the pointers in
it so they'll all be pointing to zero
which means we'd crash immediately when
we tried to call them so we'd know but
I'd rather just not have to to go
through that crash to see that so what
I'm going to do instead is just go ahead
and initialize them to what we would
then go and do after we saw the crash so
let's just skip that whole crash process
if no one has any objections basically
I'm just going to initialize those
pointers so that when the game gets the
memory Struck it has uh each thing
initialized properly so that's it that's
basically the end of it right uh don't
think there's really anything else to do
so now we're actually compiling
correctly but let's take a look uh to
see if we actually got uh in our build
directory what we wanted right because I
don't actually know if we did or not um
so it doesn't look like we did because I
passed that dll switch but you notice
we're still building an exy here uh and
I don't want it to build an XY that's
not what it's supposed to do so I I
still am I'm not passing uh the correct
things so let's let's double check that
I'm not doing something wrong so uh
let's see
here um maybe that because we're
specifying other things that it's a
problem I'm not entirely
sure uh let's take a look let's take a
look because all we really need to do
now is make sure that that's uh actually
getting followed is this something that
you passed to there entry point must be
defined uh that doesn't help us and if
it's link yeah what's going on there why
are we not not why are we not getting
the dll that we asked for because we
asked for a dll and we're not getting
one so basically all we have to do is
decrypt the magical switches uh and then
we will figure that out so it's still
producing an XZ what are my common
compiler
Flags uh let's see nothing suspicious
there there's an output of the map file
uh which should probably be specified
separately but that's really not going
to do it that's a separate thing
entirely that's just we will need those
to Output two different things as all uh
but yeah I don't see we're it looks like
we're outputting everything as you would
expect so I'm not sure why it's
disobeying uh my dll call I do not
actually know uh why it is disobeying
that call so there now it's producing
the map properly but it's still
producing an XZ so let's double check uh
let's see
here module definition statement the
base and deal options together
equivalent to the
library
uh a deal usually contains exports yes I
know we're going to do that in a second
but what I want to know is why won't you
build a dll for me I just want you to
out I just want to see I just want to
visually see this you're outputting it
uh CL Flags to make a dll so please
uh tell me what does stack Overflow say
here's your big chance to redeem
yourself stack Overflow be correct about
something let's take a
look
um uh what is
this um this doesn't
look this doesn't look useful this
doesn't look useful at all
actually um no
no no come on people how hard could this
be I mean seriously there should just be
like a thing that's like here's how you
build a dll right I mean how how how
hard is this normally what I do is I go
I go open up one of my existing projects
that builds a dll and I look at what it
does uh but of course I'm trying to go
through the steps I would have to go
through if I didn't have anything uh so
I can't actually do that so why Miss
finicki do you not seem to want to do
that it says right here the deal option
builds a dll as the main output file I
am passing it but it doesn't actually
seem to do anything uh now if it's if
it's not followed by slash link if I
just do that it says entry point must be
defined so maybe what's happening uh I'm
going to guess I'm going to hope this is
my hope that this was that passing it
after the link thing actually makes it
not work and this makes it work because
we don't specify a dll main which is
something we would actually probably
need to do so let's hope that this is
the correct switch and we'll go add the
dll main uh and and then hope that that
was actually doing it properly so I'm
going to I'm going to hope that that's
true and then it's just like if you put
it after the slash link it doesn't work
because because it doesn't all right uh
so basically what we need to do here is
inside handmade uh. CPP right um we
still have the problem of we basically
still have the problem that we need to
make a win32 version so we have our
win32 handmade uh sort of Library thing
but we also have our our our
win32 uh handmade game or something like
that so we've got we've basic got two
win32 things happening if that makes
sense uh so basically what I want to do
uh
because how should I say this
executables have the same thing dlls
have the same thing as executables
that's a good way to say it windows will
still call us when even if we're loaded
as a d it will still call into us for no
real reason other than to give us a
chance to do startup stuff uh so really
we don't actually need Windows to do
that but Windows is going to do that so
even though we're building a chunk of
code that we don't actually need it to
jump into I don't know if there's a way
to tell it just don't bother jumping
into us so what we need to do is just
put a little stub in there now we could
do that in one of two ways um in fact
maybe this is an easier way to do it I
don't know um
like we could we could not do this we
could just stick a stub at the bottom of
handmade. CPP right you could go in here
uh and do something like this um but it
maybe is a little uglier right we could
do something um uh like say okay if it's
handmade win32 right uh then we just
stick the stub in here because it isn't
actually code that anyone has to read uh
and it could go below here I don't know
how I feel about that like I said I like
to keep the codes segregated in multiple
files uh but we could and so basically
what we would need to do I I'll do it in
here and then we can kind of look at it
and decide whether we care about that
and whether we want to move it out
basically we've got this thing here um
which is dll Main and dll Main basically
uh is essentially the same as wind main
right uh basically it's just a thing
where this happens we have to include
windows. to Define these things uh and
then we we just go ahead and we have to
process uh this call now I don't
actually think there's almost anything
that you need to do I think it's all
pretty root uh let's take look those are
Community additions do we have
a uh is there there it is using Dynamic
link libraries creating a simple Dynamic
link Library there should be just the
bare minimum uh yeah of of stuff that we
would need to do in a dynamic link
Library
um let's see this doesn't seem to be
this is not what I want this is not what
I want I want something that just shows
me the minimum set of things to do in a
dll main uh let's see here let's see
here we go so basically this is what
where Windows is going to call us back
in our dll when that dll gets loaded
into memory by another process which in
this case is also going to be our
process so basically these are the
things that it's going to ask us to do
attach uh detach and so on it's
basically saying okay process attach
thread attach thread detach process
detach so it'll call us at this dll main
every time a process or a thread starts
using the dll or stops using the dll we
don't need to do anything because we're
not going to master any resources right
the whole point of this platform nonp
specific code is that it doesn't do
anything other than respond to calls uh
from the platform layer itself so really
all we should have to do honestly is
just return true it looks like there's
absolutely nothing uh that we would have
to do here so I think we can just do
that uh and leave it uh at that um
however uh okay so uh what's the problem
here if I actually compile this it says
entry point must be defined I have the
DL name that you asked me
for so why are you complaining this is
the part part where I'm not sure if the
slash D the excuse me uh the SL dll is
actually working of course Let's uh
let's take a look here if I was to go
into win32 handmade and put a win Main
in here would that compile and if it
does yeah yeah we're sad so it's still
not building a
dll so Windows why are you not building
a dll just tell me you know you don't
have to be kg why not uh I really don't
understand why uh let's see let's see
what is the reason
why
um I'm not sure I honestly don't know I
must be forgetting something and it's
going to be just the standard thing
where you kind of slap your head and go
H and feel stupid at the end of it but
let's see
here uh let's
see surely there's just a simple dll
example or something that I can just see
what it is so we've done this
um that's but this is not the following
example is the source code needed to
create a simple dll but this doesn't
even require I guess so is it just that
we haven't exported any functions is
that the
problem well I guess we're going to have
to do that anyway so I'll talk about
that and we'll see uh we'll see if
that's the case all right uh so
basically what has to
happen in order for a dll to export
entry points basically because remember
the compiler is going to compile this
code it's going to Output a dll for us
and a dll is something that's
essentially executable code it's
essentially the same as an exy right but
it has table in it of places in the code
marked by strings so you can basically
say get proc address like we did before
pass it a string it will look at the dll
and it's got a string table in there
that Maps strings to locations in the
code so that you can basically do
linking at runtime dynamically which is
Squad it's called a dynamic link Library
uh and what we will have to do in order
for this to happen is we will have to
actually have some things that are
exported now one way to do things that
are exported is to put deal speec dll
export in the code this is just some
crazy syntactic stuff that Microsoft's
compiler uh basically uses to tell you
that the thing is that is being
exported the function that it's tagged
on is going to be exported we can use
that uh but another thing we can do is
we can just specify what the exports are
uh directly and I don't actually
remember exactly how to do those but
they're actually uh pretty
straightforward if I remember correctly
uh basically it's like uh yeah it's this
so you can actually just on the link
line if you don't want to CR up your
code with Windows specific stuff uh
which we'd like to minimize as much as
possible you can use SL export um on the
link line to basically say that a
particular piece of code is going to be
SL exort now uh there's one other
there's one caveat to that that we'll
see in a second uh but basically slash
export I don't know where it's got the
uh the Define for that should have it in
here
somewhere let's see
msbc exort Linker switch
okay let's see here exports
function my net is slow or maybe it's
just msdn that's slow all right so
basically this right uh so basically
what this does is you can basically say
Okay I want to export um a particular
name I want to export it and I can just
give the name of the function there but
there's a caveat here that we'll see in
a second uh basically okay I'll put it
in and you could see what I mean so I'm
going to do export entry name here I'm
going to say that want to export get
sound samples CU we said we wanted to
export that and I also want to export
game update and render right so I just
want to do those two things right well
okay guess I got to put
them after the link
line like that all right uh
so yeah I just don't know I I'm failing
tonight this might be an all of Shame
moment because I I'm failing just to
know what the compiler switches are to
do the thing that I actually needed to
do
um I really need this thing to actually
build a dll for me but it really doesn't
seem to want to uh but now that I've got
some exports it seems like it's actually
doing it so maybe the whole time it was
really just upset about that I don't
know U but it's still outputting an
executable you can see that it's
outputting an executable uh which is
which is kind of weird but anyway all
right uh and but it's even it's creating
a lib do you notice that so it's
actually creating an import Library as
if it was about to build a DL uh and
even an export tape so
very strange uh but let's just finish
what we were doing and then we'll go try
to debug that some more so anyway uh
I've got the exports here game update
and render G get sound samples uh but
there's a rub basically which is that we
have not actually marked up these
functions to avoid having them uh be
name mangled and I don't know if you
remember uh the name mangling stuff I
showed where C++ mangles the names in
order to work with old school C linkers
there's this sort of whole process I I
talked about it in detail hopefully you
guys
remember so if we look at what these
functions actually get called they ain't
called uh game get sound samples and
game update and render their names are
something totally different so in order
to make sure that they don't essentially
get
um that they don't get mangled in that
way I can put a thing called exter and C
in front of them if that makes sense uh
and what extern C does and do not ask me
where they came up with this particular
syntax it's very different from just
about anything else what xtern C does is
it says okay this function in particular
it needs to be uh following the the old
school C convention don't mangle the
name uh right and so if we take a look
at what actually gets output hopefully
it will get output in the map as well so
I can actually show you
um map uh let's see uh update and render
update and
render uh
see oh why did I use that that's not
what I meant to use I used the wrong F
function there date and render okay
there we go so here's the simple demo uh
of this so before extern c game update
and render I'm going to do the build I'm
going to look at the map file which
remember I said is a thing that gets
outputed that shows us where all our
functions are and now I look at what the
names of these things are well here's
the name mangled version of that right
it's total crazy town right it's like
it's not the name at all okay uh and and
so if I go in now and I add that extern
c you can see now that it will change it
to what I actually wanted which is just
the straight name game update and render
game get sound samples right so that's
exactly what I wanted uh and that's it
so the only thing we have to do now is
uh try to convince msvc to Output A.D
now I suspect because it actually
imported the it I suspect because of the
way that it did this that we could
actually load the executable directly um
I feel like it's just naming it exy or
something but hold on a second we'll
actually try that uh and and see so
basically if I go up here instead of
letting loading handmade. uh D I load
handmade. exe I just want to see what
actually happens so let's go ahead and
step into our code here when I load the
game code I want to see what happens
yeah so it it's opening up this right
it's opening up this guy uh and then it
goes ahead and ask for game update and
render and it got it right so there we
go uh and hey look at that it's actually
uh well no actually I think it's it's
probably not quite working at that point
uh because we should have seen the we're
not actually getting the game code
running let's see there but it actually
got update and render it got an address
back for it and it got an address back
from for sound samples as well uh so I'm
not sure is valid oh right
typo not valid then we overwrite it so
let's take a look now
yeah so who knows why we'll have to
figure out why Windows is deciding to to
create an exe instead of a dll we don't
know yet but basically it doesn't matter
for our current purposes maybe we'll do
it in the Q&A because I'm sure someone
on the stream uh has already thought of
what the problem is so basically what
we're doing here is now we're actually
loading our own code dynamically right
we're actually loading out of that XZ
that was produced uh we're doing the
load ourselves this handmade. exe right
so now what we could do if we wanted to
um we can make it so that we can just
reload that code on demand essentially
right uh so if we want to we can say
okay this is win32 load code uh we could
also do uh something like this win32
unload game code right uh which would
basically
be taking this win32 game code thing
here uh and it will take one of these
and unload it just just flat out uh get
rid of it right so we've got our game
code it's going to take take a pointer
to the game code and it's going to go
ahead and say if it's valid right well
actually I guess it doesn't need even
need to do that it's just going to go
ahead and do a free library uh on game
code uh dll right assuming that game
code dll was actually uh D there we go
assuming that it was actually there it's
going to free it uh and then regardless
of what it's going to do it'll just go
ahead and set this stuff uh so that
basically the game code is no longer
considered valid right it's not valid
anymore uh and this the everything is
reset to the STS game code update
render game code set down samples that
and so that'll unload our game code
right uh so let's see No Object file
generated unlo game code un reference
local function okay well that's fine
because we're about to use it so now if
we really wanted to be absurd which I
don't want to be but I'm just going to
demonstrate the fact that we could could
be absurd if we wanted to in
theory uh we could go ahead and actually
just load and unload the game code every
time through this Loop right there's
actually no reason why we couldn't do
that right I can go in here and I can
say all right I'm going to take this
game code and I'm going to load and I'm
going to unload it um every time right
so there's the there's the load
oops spor out key class there's the load
there's the unload so what I'll do do is
I'll go into uh our running thing at the
top of the loop I'll load the game code
in and after we're done with our game
Loop I'll just unload it right um which
one of these let's see here that's while
Global running so there we go and that's
the yeah s uh so in theory I think
that'll actually work but it'll probably
tank our frame rate but I think it
actually would work let's find out yeah
so it totally it's going to ruin things
a bit for us but you know it appears to
work and you can actually see it if you
actually look in here if we look at our
history you can see us unload and load
unload and load unload and load all the
time
right uh so basically what's happening
there is it's actually going to load and
unload uh this guy uh the stuff that we
built in here all the time now what we
can do is we can go in here and say now
we we we actually have a problem I just
realized um we still have a a static
variable in here right that t sign
should have gotten moved out to the game
state but it never did uh so we need we
need to get rid of all our local persist
because there shouldn't have been any
more of those and that's going to cause
a problem because those things are in
the D so if it gets loaded and unloaded
they're going to reset every time uh so
we've got a t sign here let's go ahead
and uh and and fix that so that t sign
actually gets initialized properly so in
the game State when we set the tone
Hertz uh we're going to go ahead and set
the T sign equal to 0.0f and now when T
sign uh gets used we're actually going
to use uh sort of the game State T sign
right uh so let's see here game State
and all I'm doing there really very
straightforward right I'm just I had a a
old static variable a local persistent
variable and I don't want that because
we're we don't want anything stored in
the dll we just want everything to come
in in the standard memory like we
planned um and so I'm going to go ahead
and do that uh and now we just need to
pass that game State uh because
presumably um this does not take that
currently so here we go game state do
right up in
there so game output sound now has to
take the game state but other than that
everything is good and let's rerun it
there we go good as new and somehow that
is so fast that we actually can do it
every frame uh I guess because our code
is so small it's a little surprising but
it kind of works right uh now in theory
and I don't know because we're loading
and unloading it so fast the compiler
may not be able to slip in there to
actually write the file uh in Theory
what we should be able to do if we
really want to right uh is while this is
running we should now be able to do some
really crazy town stuff uh right we
should be able to come in here and say
okay uh I don't know the game's running
uh but if I wanted to I could come in
here and say that uh this was actually
going to be shifted up 16 instead right
uh when I compile that uh yeah so that's
the problem is it can't ever open it for
writing you see how that's happening so
I got to do the next step of my process
before we can really get to the
awesomeness all right that's okay cu the
next step is pretty darn
trivial the next step is pretty darn
trivial so uh all we have to do now is
we're loading and unloading this code
every frame but we're loading and
unloading it so fast uh that the
compiler doesn't actually have a chance
to write to the file because it's always
being opened uh by ours so I guess one
thing I could do here's a here's an
easier way to do it than what I was
going to do so let's let's actually try
to verify that this works first and then
we'll go back and do it uh the fancier
way because we're almost out of time and
so maybe the fancier way we'll have to
wait till tomorrow so uh where is my
load game code so here's my load game
code so all I'm going to do uh is I'm
going to load the game code before we
enter here right uh but then I'm going
to take the free code the the um the
unload game code right and I'm actually
just going to do at the top of the loop
uh I'm going to do the unload game code
and then I'm going to do the load game
code immediately after right and I'm G
to actually I think what I want to do
here uh well no this is fine so we'll
basically just do this right so there we
go like that uh so all I'm going to do
here is I'm going to basically say you
know I've got a counter uh load counter
and that load counter is going to be
like every 60 frames or something like
that right so every two seconds maybe
we'll make it a little bit more right
like that uh and what I'm going to do
here is basically say if the load
counter is greater than 120 uh then
we'll reset the load counter so that we
just do it uh every few times uh through
the loop if that makes sense that's all
we're going to do uh so we will say
every time through the loop we increment
the load counter this will give us uh
120 frames at 30 frames a second is like
4 seconds that should give the compiler
some time uh to open the file so that's
that's that's all I did is I just said
all right let's let's only unload and
load it uh that frequently if that makes
sense so off we go um let's see now if
we can actually get the file to open uh
at some point so let's see here can we
do it can we do it can we do it no we
can't um
well I wonder if that's I wonder if I'm
doing something wrong in terms of
freeing the library because that could
also be the case Free Library uh we are
still we are doing the Free Library
although this should actually
do I should actually set this so that
it's clear What's Happening Here for
some reason uh that is oh well duh I
don't know why I thought that was going
to make it any better now that I think
about it that's just dumb uh because
basically yeah basically I still have to
do one more step with the problem
process because this will still only
leave it unlocked in between there just
because I'm not reloading it again
obviously the dll will be locked while
it's being used so I got to do one more
step of the process right what I got to
do is I got to make it so that I'm not
locking the thing that the compiler is
outputting to to right so the way that
I'm going to do that is I'm just going
to when I do the reload I'm just going
to copy that file right I'm just going
to use the copy file call which is a
Windows call uh right copy file um and
the copy file function just basically
takes two things and does the copy right
it just takes an existing file and a new
file and it copies from the existing to
the new one that's it and you can pass
it whether you want it to fail if the
new file exists or not to so if you want
to always create a new one which we
don't uh so all I'm going to do is B
basically like call there's something
called let's say handmade
temp. and I'm going to copy handmade.
exe to that handmade temp right that's
all I'm going to do nothing nothing
particularly weird there I'm going to do
that copy right and the copy is going to
allow me to lock a file that is not the
file that the compiler is outputting to
right pretty straightforward uh so I
know that'll work because now I'm not
locking that file anymore I'm I'm
locking a I'm locking a different file
and I know that I will do the copy when
I have it unlocked so uh let's take a
look at this here oops that's not good
looks like my copy did not work
particularly
well did that actually work where's my
copy
file uh oh because we're running in the
data directory as well aren't we um okay
so we need to do one more thing
uh which is a little janky okay but we
can get we can get around that for the
time being all right so basically the
problem here though is this stuff only
works this is only without a path this
is only going to work if this stuff is
in the current directory so what I need
to do temporarily is set the current
directory to that because until we do
the full thing which I guess we'll have
to again wait till tomorrow to do uh we
don't have we don't know where we're
looking for stuff we don't know where
those DLS are going to be so we don't
really want a handmade uh we don't
really want to hardcode this path in
there so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to actually just run it in the
build directory where everything is uh
and that should actually work right and
so now you can see if I look in here uh
it actually did that it did that copy
that I wanted to do uh and it should be
doing that copy every so often right
because remember I put a timer on there
well not timer it's a frame counter on
there uh so that it'll periodically do
it so now uh when I go in here in theory
I should be be able to actually write to
the file uh but I don't actually know
let's see um error writing to program
database handmade.
pdb oh but oh okay uh so we do have one
more problem which is that the the
debugger itself is locking our pdb file
uh as well uh which is definitely not
what we wanted it to do oh debugger
debugger well all right so we can still
make this happen uh in the short term
here uh we can run we can run our game
outside of the debugger uh and we can do
this I suppose let's see here there we
go
um so there you go uh this is now
actually doing what we wanted it to do
uh which is basically we can edit the
code uh and have it update while we're
running right uh and we don't actually
have to stop the executable and again
the state is all actually there as well
right there's no we could get to the
boss fight change the code and see it
update in real time and without any
actual without having to do anything
right so it's it's sort of as good as
having a scripting language in some
sense it basically allows us if we want
to uh to edit all the code and we can do
all sorts of weird stuff here right we
could decide that this was you know some
other thing uh and that would just be
you know I don't know whatever you can
see when whenever it updates we don't
even know what it is but you can play
with the patterns here uh and get pretty
immediate feedback now the feedback is
not quite instant because we're waiting
for seconds between reloads uh but what
we'll see we're out of time tonight what
we'll see tomorrow when we do all the
rest of the stuff that has to back this
up cuz we only just got it in with the
wire tonight uh what what we'll see
tomorrow when we do the rest of this
backs up is how to make that basically
instantaneous so that as soon as we hit
um recompile it'll reload so there you
go that was just something again like I
thought we deserve to do something fun
because we had done so much uh sort of
just wrote stuff with the win32 API
where we kind of just had to play by its
rules and do what it wanted us to do so
that we could get access to the stuff
that we wanted to I thought maybe it'd
be fun to do something cool with the win
32 API uh that lets us do something
interesting inter and this is not
specific to win32 you can do these same
sorts of Tricks um on other platforms as
well because almost every platform um
supports Dynamic linking so anyway this
is kind of kind of awesome I like this
sort of thing because it just makes it
feel a lot cooler when you can code uh
to just do that and then it's like once
you uh once you change the thing it uh I
don't know it just it just makes it cool
so you can see now we're only clearing
like half the screen right or whatever
um etc etc but we've got a lot this gets
even this gets way cooler um so we'll
we'll do a much much cooler version of
this as well sometime soon let's also do
I don't know let's let's let's let's
play with the with the size of the
gradient maybe and it's just fun to to
watch it go sometimes right um there's
there's one that's sort of wider right
and so on so anyway that's pretty cool I
hope you enjoyed that little trick uh
we're not done with it it's not nearly
as cool as it's going to be tomorrow but
we only barely got in there and also we
do not know I still don't know why
it's outputting an
exy I I got to go I'll go look at my
other stuff and find out why I don't or
you know I I don't know because it's it
still seems to want to do an ex export
and I do not know why all right um so
anyway there we go we've basically taken
I mean that was not very much work right
all we did we did it extremely you know
all the work that people put into
scripting languages and like at the end
of the day there's a lot of stuff you
could could just do and see if you just
tried right and so this is an example of
how to do that um and now you can reload
all your code not just your scripting
language code at runtime right so we can
reload all the engine code too if we
want to uh which is going to be pretty
awesome uh now there's a problem of
course which is if the game crashes what
do you do but that's the thing we're
going to take care of tomorrow uh so
anyway so for tonight just to recap what
we did as we enter the Q&A here please
uh make sure your questions include
sorator in them so I'll see them and try
to keep them on we did today or past but
I'm just going to do a quick recap here
because I went pretty fast through
everything there basically what we did
is we took our build.bat file we decided
to build two things instead of one thing
we split the game code into one uh
basically executable chunk and the uh
platform code into another executable
chunk right we then have the platform
executable chunk load and whenever it
wants to it will reload the game
executable chunk it then calls uh
Windows to ask it to give it the address
of functions in that Chunk in the chunk
that it loaded it says where are the
where is the sound samples function and
the update and render function because
that's the two functions that I need to
call it gets those back from Windows it
calls them and when it calls them it
passes in a struct in addition to the
structs we already defined like the
offscreen buffer and that sort of stuff
in addition to those we also pass in any
functions that we need it to call us
back at right so any calls that go back
to the platform layer um which are only
debug calls at the moment but if we had
any that were actually real calls uh we
could pass those right those get passed
in so that the game has pointers back to
where the functions are in the main
executable as well uh that's all we did
and then we just put in a simple frame
counter so that every 120 frames it
tries to reload the game code that's all
we did uh in the code um proper at this
time so there you go uh pretty simple
really straightforward if you architect
the code correctly in the first place
like we did this is Trivial uh and I
hopefully you saw that it was trivial in
fact most of the work we have to do is
figuring out which darn switch to pass
to cl to get it output the dll that was
like most of the time uh but yeah but
there you go so I'll go to the questions
now
okay
[Music]
um so a bunch of people say they think
maybe SL l d uh will tell it to Output a
DL not an executable so let's try that
and hope that they're right because yeah
I don't we don't I mean we don't have to
produce a dll as you saw an executable
works fine but it just seems nicer to to
do a dll because that's I don't know why
it just that's what people do um so
let's try it
LD uh incremental link oh so one of the
things we also you know I forgot to do
this one of the things we also should do
on our common Linker frags is is turn
off the incremental Linker um because
since we build everything from scratch
every time that's just wasting
everyone's time uh is it incremental
no okay uh so let's see I'm going to go
in here to our build directory I'm going
to delete a handmade Star right so
that's gone uh and then I am going to
rebuild let's see what we get
here yay okay thank you stream uh that
is what we needed we just needed to
specify some extra sauce here to just
tell it I guess the ldld switch this
this/ dll switch I guess tells the
Linker output of DL but the /ld switch
tells the compiler to do a dll and this
must mark it so that it gets an exi name
instead of a dll I I I don't actually
know the interaction of these switches
I'm not sure it might be that we don't
need this one anymore as well uh like
once you pass this it may automatically
imply that I'm not sure let's take a
look um yeah so it looks like we can
just pass that uh so basically I guess
it's just if you happen to be calling CL
which is itself going to summon the
Linker uh you dold I guess is how that
works I'm not sure but thank you stream
for for that's that's really all we
needed to get that going so uh what we
can do now is do what we wanted to do
here which is instead of loading
handmade. exe we can load handmade.
dll okay and I'm going to put the to-dos
in here as well so Casey to-do uh need
to get the proper path here right um and
to
do automatic determination of when
updates are necessary okay just snuggle
those in there for
tomorrow
okay use a key press to unload and key
press to load uh no so we're going to do
something better than a key press to
load and unload tomorrow so we should be
we should be fine with
that uh so we have small code right now
how does dynamic linking and compiling
to an exy work with huge games that are
gigs well first of all the reason most
huge games are huge is because they are
not written right um I know that's kind
of a strong thing to say but basically
like basically this game will never get
huge uh we will never have a 20 gigabyte
executable that's just not going to
happen um so we really don't have to
worry about it the reason that that sort
of thing happens is because of bad
programming decisions basically um and
sometimes those sometimes those bad
programming decisions aren't bad in the
sense that like they were made because
there's a thousand programmers on the
project and there's no way to actually
get everyone to do the right thing so it
was just better to have the thing be 20
gigs and whatever and that's so I'm not
trying to point the finger at people and
say you were stupid or anything uh you
may well have been smart and it was the
only thing that you could do but when
you are architecting things properly you
will never ever no matter how complex
the game is is you will never have a 20
GB executable that's just not going to
happen uh so you're pretty much
safe uh let's see
here for people suggesting find first
change notification don't spoiler
tomorrow's stream I'm not going to tell
you what we're using we're going to use
some stuff tomorrow that's for tomorrow
no spoilers uh let's see here
I always have problems with loops and
how they work have you in all your years
of coding learned an easy way to help
with
loops that I do not totally understand
ci12
um I mean a loop is just very simple a
loop basically is
this right a loop is basically some
point in your code and you do some code
and then when you get to the end of it
you go to back to the to the point in
the code right and basically the only
thing that a loop is is a way of
conveniently writing like a while loop
right where I have while you know
something is true um do some stuff right
basically a while loop all of these just
get turned into this form uh this is
just basically if something is true go
to top else don't
right so basically this is a loop the
condition goes in here right the stuff
you do goes in here all these are and
all of C Loops are is basically the
stuff that has to get done happens right
and in fact um in this case we would
skip the first one so a while loop
checks at first so if something is true
it does the stuff right then it goes to
the then it goes back to the top uh and
if something isn't true it just doesn't
right so really it's just you can
imagine it just executing line by line
you can turn any Loop into just an if
statement and a go-to really right
there's not there's really nothing to it
uh so I don't know if you have a more
specific question I could try to answer
it but Loops you don't have to think of
them as something special goto like jump
is the only thing that actually exists
go-to is the only thing that actually
exists at the CPU Loops are purely
syntactic sugar that highle languages
put on top of a go-to that is all they
are um so
yeah so
yeah let's take a look here
do you recommend playing around with
creating dll files or is it mainly used
in specific cases uh no I recommend
playing around with them all the time
yeah being able to dynamically load code
is a great idea so play around with them
see what you can do with them I mean you
saw how easy it is all you have to do is
say here's an entry point I need to
exported and then you can get proc
address it and off you go so yeah see
what you can do with it I mean uh go to
town that's what I would say
uh let's
see can someone now create a dummy
handmade. D and use it to intercept the
game update and render function to get a
pointer to game memory and change stuff
is security something you will cover in
a later stream this is by ambiguous
Panda so uh I don't know why that would
be relevant so one of the important
things so security is one of those
things where I don't feel like people
really understand it usually um they
tend to think that something is more or
less secure based on a bunch of stuff
that isn't actually relevant to its
security so if you think about the the
threat model that you're talking about
basically I've got a handmade. exe and
I've got a handmade.
dll and the only threat model that I've
introduced now that didn't exist
previously would be if for some reason
someone had right privileges to
handmade. dll but didn't have right
privileges to handmade. exe since they
were both installed by the same user at
the same time who installed the game in
the same
directory uh I'm not exactly sure why
you would ever think it was less secure
to load exy out of two files executable
code out of two files than
one it just really doesn't make any
sense right um because whoever overwrote
handmade. DL could have just overwrote
handmade. exe right there's no reason
for them to there's no reason for them
to attack handmade. DL because it
doesn't have any weaker security than
hand me.exe had uh all virus Checkers
understand that there's code in dll and
XZ so there isn't such a thing as a
place where it's like checking one or
the other um so basically yeah there's
really
no there's really no security hold there
um at least not one that I can think of
so
also I think security for games is silly
like that should just been built in the
OS the fact that games have to even
think about security is ridiculous
because security should Games should run
in a sandbox they're not an application
that interconnects so like the fact you
should be able to ship as many security
holes as you want in a game because game
should always run now it's windows's
entire fault that that isn't true uh
that was just a colossal uh a colossal
um bollocking up as they
say let's see here
um let's see I'm going to post this
again because I'm sure mine got buried
we have a tiny application right now so
with code that takes minutes to compile
how do we do what we just did okay so
I'm going to say this
again uh I already answered part of that
question but I'm going to answer it
again because you asked it slightly
differently this time you asked about
taking minutes to compile if your code
ever takes minutes to compile you've
done it wrong
code should take less than 10 seconds to
compile period if your code takes more
than 10 seconds to
compile you need to stop and figure out
why you have written code that way
because that is a bad way to write code
period um and I know there's a lot of
people who will disagree with that
statement but they're wrong like
I I do not I have never encountered
something so complicated that it could
not compile in less than 10
seconds so
that's really all I can say um I really
don't care what it is like it's just
compilers are extraordinarily fast and
machines are extraordinarily fast now
and the reason that things take 10
minutes to compile is because people
decided to use all kinds of weird
template metaprogramming nonsense and
stuff that slows the compiler down
tremendously and if you go that route
then you basically has sacrificed all of
the benefits that you could have had uh
and it's just a really bad programming
decision so don't make that that
decision never make that decision and
you won't ever have to worry about it if
you do make that decision all bets are
off and I really can't help you right
you're in a situation that you've sort
of created uh and then you will have to
do all sorts of things like now you have
to implement an entire scripting
language and a debugger and an Optimizer
for the scripting language because you
made the poor decision to write code
that takes multiple minutes to compile
right so yeah what can you do now what I
will say is verify that you really are
in that position can you break your huge
amount of code up into multiple dlls and
only reload the ones that changed right
um you know can you make if you've got
20 Gigabytes of code can you break that
into 200 DLS and then you only rebuild
one dll and it gets reloaded right I
mean there's an option for you
potentially uh but there's a lot of
headaches that go around along with
doing something like that so again I
don't know so the right decision in my
opinion is if your code takes longer
than 10 seconds to compile you've done
something wrong assume that that is true
uh and build your project from
there would you be able to load the deal
yourself using read file and Implement
get proc address as well assuming
there's an easy way to make the memory
executable like map yes uh you totally
can do that the reason I'm not doing
that is because we would like the
debugger to
understand the code uh so what you have
to what you have to understand is that a
debugger runs by looking at the
executable that it is debugging and
loading corresponding debug info for
that executable when a dynamic link
library is loaded that is a new set of
code that is brought in and the debug
information for that code is not present
in the debug info for the main
executable so it has to go and find the
debug information for that dll now the
way that it does this is because loading
the dll through windows' standard hooks
right load Library Free Library the
debugger sees those happen and it knows
to go get the debug info when it sees
those happen for the dlls that it sees
loading if we implement the load
ourselves then we get into a situation
where the debugger doesn't know we've
loaded that code so we can't load the
debug information and we can't step
through the code that we've loaded right
um you could go ahead and write a symbol
server that the debugger connected to
and Implement your own symbol server
which made up for this shortcoming or
stuff like this potentially um which
then faked the symbols for the
executable to look like they were
whatever the symbols were for the loaded
code in some back Channel like you could
do stuff uh to patch that hole but it's
a real long road if you decide to go
that route um so basically the reason
that we're using Windows to load this uh
and the reason that we'll use like other
platforms as well when we Implement like
this on on Linux will do the same thing
in their way uh the reason that you do
that is specifically because we want the
debugger to understand that we loaded
that code and to support us which it can
do if we go through the standard
Channel let us
see is this technique still possible
without using the passing of a large
memory block between the dll and the
XZ uh
uh
well
well so I believe the answer should
generally be
yes let me let me let me state it this
way
as long as the dll code always gets its
memory from the main executable you will
be fine now there's multiple ways that
this can happen one way that it could
happen would be to do it the way that
I'm doing it right now with the those
debug calls where when the dll gets
loaded it basically gets handed some
pointers and then you call those
pointers when you want more
memory because that way all the memory
is still allocated in the executable and
there's no issues with what happens when
the dll gets
unloaded
but uh by default that is already sort
of what happens in Windows because what
happens is when the dll gets loaded if
you use well it's not really true if
you're using static
linking I don't know what happens if you
just call new like or malok directly
from the dll I think when you unload it
it'll get freed if it was a statically
linked C runtime library in the dll now
what you can do is you can change to
using a dynamic C runtime Library which
means that both the executable and the
dll that you load will share a dll that
is the C runtime Library so they both
call into that but in order to do that
you would have to go onto the build line
and you'd have to change this minus Mt
to a minus MD or whatever it is I don't
remember uh so I mean so the short
answer is yes it certainly can work
without the monolithic block but the
answer is no you can't just do it really
neilly you have to actually think about
where that memory is coming from and
make sure that it's coming from a place
that won't get um purged when the dll
gets unloaded so you can definitely make
it work um but just you have to be aware
that it's not free um it does take a
little bit of planning but it's it's
it's it still
works uh
okay what's
next does the dll prevent the compiler
from inlining uh it prevents the
compiler from inlining across the dll
boundary uh but as you've noticed we
don't need that to happen right um we
have like basically our entire game runs
inside this function right um the entire
game is is going to be in here uh so you
call game update and render and
everything that happens in the game is
called off here so all of the in that
will have to happen in the game happens
inside the dll we never need to inline
across that boundary um so we don't have
to worry about that but no if if for
some reason you wanted to have lots of
functions in the dll that were small and
were called from the platform layer and
you were counting on inlining to make
that fast that is a problem and that
will not work uh but you know don't do
that how are we going to implement DLS
on Linux Mac uh they B they basically
have the same thing so they basically
have shared Library as well uh there's
like there's just they're just called
different things but they they the
same uh let's
see are there vods for this series I
just stumbled upon it and really want to
catch up yes handmad her.org um if you
go to handmade her.org you will have
everything that you need uh basically
news and forums you click on that um and
then an episode guide we'll have a bunch
of stuff for you that you need so that
is what you
want uh let's see
here
um I'm looking for a new
question that is on
topic
uh are you ever going to write the
platform layers for other platforms on
the stream in the far future yes um at
the moment if you just want uh a
platform layer uh to use you can go to
so at handmade here.org if you click on
that news and forums thing again there's
a coding resources page and people have
already ported it uh to both sdl and Mac
native um so if you want to just run it
on another platform that's actually
pretty trivial because people already
did the hard work for you if you want to
watch me Port it that won't happen for
quite some time because basically
porting work is just straightforward
Grimble work of take the things we did
in win 32 and do them in Linux there's
nothing it's literally as uninteresting
as it gets so now that we have one
platform layer working I'm not going to
spend any more time on platform layers
until we go to ship things um but if you
just want to get it running right now
you can go access those
resources is the process roughly the
same for doing the Linux equivalent with
shared libraries having seen your
windows version with a couple hours of
Googling and GCC clang documentation
digging be likely to get me there or
should I be looking for something
specific uh yeah I think so I don't know
if David gal is planning to do so if you
go again to coding resources David G has
done this awesome thing called handmade
penguin uh that if you go look on here
it's just it's got all sorts of stuff
that you want to know if you're doing a
Linux version of this in fact it's
probably I'm going to guess and I don't
know but I'm going to guess that this is
a better resource than looking at how I
will port to Linux because I'm I'm less
knowledge about Linux than he is I
suspect um so if he decides to do the
dll loading you may be able to wait for
him to do it for you because he may
already understand that stuff uh really
well um if not then yes I do think that
it shouldn't take too long to implement
what I just did because you're just
looking for three things how to export
functions from something in a way so
that you could basically call the
compiler and say Here's a make a dynamic
library with these functions exported
then you just need load library and get
proc address well and free library right
so you basically just have those things
to do if you can find those that's all
you need right right um tomorrow we'll
do some other fancier stuff and so you
may need a couple other things but you
know uh if you just want the
basics the internet FTW says your pound
Define type def magic kind of bugs me in
that it hides the arguments return type
away from the implementation how much of
a win is having the signature in one
place uh the answer is it depends how
many times it happens so for these it's
probably no big deal uh I would say just
if you don't like it don't do it um the
the person who's asking the question is
asking about these uh sorts of things
that I do to make it so that you never
have to change what the parameters are
in multiple places uh for a call back
and yeah you you don't have to do that
uh if you'd rather not do it then you
you don't have to um but there are
certain cases where I would strongly
advise that you do do it and those are
places where you have lots of the same
type of calls so for examp example if
you're making like an entity dispatch
and you've got 300 entity types in your
system you really want to use this macro
because if you decide to change the
parameters that go to an entity dispatch
you really don't want to go change it
300 times or more depending on the
circumstance let's see
how does Windows manage memory in a dll
is there a dll process space where are
variables made with static stored how is
Heap memory manage that is allocated
from a dll so the answer is I don't
remember some of the specifics of that
um basically what happens
is uh do I have some some Ms paint going
on here
yeah uh so basically what happens let's
take a 32-bit executable because it's a
little simpler to to conceptualize um
64bit such a much bigger address space
uh so basically here's 2 gabt of memory
and here's 2 gabt of memory here uh
totaling four gigabyt of memory which
for 32 bits of address space is all the
address space there is right uh 4
gigabytes is the maximum addressable
memory uh for for 32bits uh pointers
right uh so typically what happens in
Windows is you basically have the upper
2 gig so this is the 2 gig with the high
bit Set uh the the high 2 gig is for the
OS um and the low 2 gig is for you right
that's how that
works so as far as I know what happens
when you load a dll is it just flat out
picks a place in here and slams that DL
code right on in there um and basically
what it does is it uses a memory mapped
file uh to basically map uh the file so
so if this is the disc right if here's
the dis right uh you've got your XY is
on dis somewhere right there's the XY
and here's the dll is on dis somewhere
who knows where right uh basically what
happens is well I shouldn't probably
have drawn that quite so soon uh
basically what happens right is when you
start up your exy is mapped into here
somewhere right and I'm not trying to
say where I'm not trying to say that
it's low I'm just saying somewhere in
your address bace your exes uh file gets
mapped in in and then your dll's file
gets mapped in when you load it right uh
and that is how the code gets mapped in
now when you allocate
memory basically there's stuff in here
uh there's different ways of allocating
memory right if a dll were to call
virtual
alloc uh I don't know whether that
counts towards the exy charge or the dll
charge
so so this is why I say I don't remember
this specifics well enough for an exie
if you call virtual Alo like we are it
basically takes some range of your
executable and reserves it for use as
memory and you get back a pointer to it
so now the exie is pointing to it when
uh you leave when you when you call
virtual free you can free it or when
your exie dies obviously that
reservation goes away and all of the
information Windows stored about that
page goes away but with the dll I don't
know if it remembers virtual allocs from
dlls or not my
my assumption is that it doesn't um but
I could be wrong about that my
assumption is that you could virtual
alloc from a dll it would alock in here
in your memory space and that it would
just stay and when you unload the dll it
would still be there and the XC could
use it but I don't know if that's true
um the reason that I think that's
true uh
so I'll tell you why I think that's true
uh but you will have to go and verify it
um yourself basically
uh so here's virtual
Alec right that's this is what it looks
like and virtual Alec takes an address
it says this is where I want the memory
to be it can be zero if you just want
Windows to pick an address here's how
big I want it uh here's the type of
allocation I want and here's the memory
protection for it right well nowhere in
that code did it have a module handle
right so when you call this Windows
doesn't actually know who's calling it
other than the information about the
thread itself that called it right it
has some way of determining which thread
called it but that's about it so because
that occurs let's say we go ahead and do
a get proc address uh so we load this
dll and there's a procedure in here we
do a get proc address and that procedure
calls virtual aloc we do a get proc
address in the XE we now have a pointer
into this code right it's just a pointer
it's just like any other function
pointer when we dispatch into that from
the XZ
and then it calls virtual aloc I don't
see how Windows would even know that the
virtual alloc call was coming from the
dll does that make sense so basically my
assumption is uh that that like I said
um you have to be aware like I I was
answering the person before who was
saying what happens if you don't pass
memory from the execut you have to be
aware that there's a difference uh of
between code in the dlll and code in the
XZ you have to be aware of it uh but it
doesn't mean that you have to it doesn't
mean that you can't just do all the
things that you want to do so here's the
part that I don't know there's things
called heaps um that we aren't using
right now okay and that kind of looks
like herpes so let's try and draw that
again so that it actually looks like
heaps there we go heaps are a different
thing entirely uh heaps are not virtual
alet calls heaps are basic things that
have called virtual aloc in some way and
are now portioning out that virtual aloc
uh for you as you ask for stuff so
they're more like a traditional memory
allocator what I don't know is if
there's a heap created for the dll that
by default calls in the dll that are
static C runtime Library allocation
calls linked into it at link time when
the dll is linked not Dynamic link time
but statically Linked In when the dll is
produced
if there is a heap that is normally used
uh that goes with the dll and that will
be freed by Windows when the dll is
unloaded I suspect that there is and I
suspect that you would get into trouble
if you were relying on that so for
example if you call new right and the
function new inside this dll uh when it
was called gets compiled to calling an
address which uses a keep that is the
Heap from the dll in some
way I don't know right it uses a static
variable that is the heat pointer that
got allocated in dll main or God knows
what right hopefully you can follow me
why this is not ridiculous what I'm
saying uh then it could very well be
that that gets purged on exit so I guess
what I would say is there's a lot of
things that could be going on here if
you wanted to do stuff other than what I
showed you you should learn this stuff
well uh and then you should be able to
do it but as a rule of thumb I would say
that if you're only calling virtual aloc
I suspect it would never matter whether
you called it from the exie or the dll
because I don't think Windows knows
which one you're doing if you use new or
malok on the other hand those are not
operating system calls those are calls
that call into the CRT and so the same
diagram again um
right basically you have to imagine
there's a c runtime component of this
right uh so here's my XY and let's say
that both the C runtime Library uh both
my XY and my dll were statically linked
with the c runtime Library not
dynamically linked right then I look
like this the dll code has a c runtime
Library the exe has a Ser time Li
included in this is a static let's say a
static pointer to a heap that gets
initialized at startup so there's a
static heap if there's a static Heap
then that static he could very well be
used by all the calls to Malo that
happened in this dll CU remember the
call to malok exists now there's there's
code for malok in both of these and both
of them can use a different static
there's a static Heap here as well
right so depending on which compilation
unit you're in you have resolved your
calls to Malo to be calling into
different pieces of code at runtime and
all these calls to Malo may use Heap and
all these codes to Malo may use this
Heap which means two things one when
this dll gets unloaded all the Heap goes
away that it ever Al gone poof goodbye
right but the other thing it means is
you better be darn sure that you never
pass a pointer that you maled in the dll
over to the CRT where it then would call
free because now you're freeing out of a
heap that's not the Heap you allocated
out of and the same goes vice versa
don't pass in a Malo here that's going
to get freed on this guy's Heap because
now you got a heap mismatch
so the solution that a lot of people use
to fix that problem which I believe is
actually a problem like I said I don't
remember a lot of this stuff because I
don't use any of it anymore but point
being um you know it's a thing basically
what ends up happening is you've got an
XZ here right you've got your dll which
is here they then have a CRT DL so they
link dynamically with the c runtime
library now both of these guys call into
malok
right and now you're always using the
same Heap because the static Heap
pointer is the same for everybody uh so
that is one benefit to using if you're
doing crazy stuff like this which I say
crazy but it's how most people do it I
think it's crazy but if you were doing
crazy stuff like that uh that is one
reason to use a shared um a a dynamic
link library for the dll because then
everyone can just Malak and free memory
using standard new and delete or malikan
free and it just works because they're
all sharing the same code uh for this
year run time
Library okay so we're basically done
here we're out of time so let me just
double check to see what we've got uh
let's
see uh let's see
here let's see
here uh enemy Mouse doesn't Windows know
by the instruction pointers leading up
to the virtual alloc call uh no I mean
it would have to walk the stack
right um in order to know who it was
because you're not passing really
anything that would identify them I
don't think um so it could walk the
stack and try to figure out um but you
know or look at the return value address
I guess and then you see which one
that's in but you know that's that's
work that I don't think it does maybe it
does I'm not sure um but we'll
see again I don't do any of that stuff
because I don't want to rely on
operating system Behavior that I don't
have to so it's one of the reasons one
of the reasons I don't know that answer
off hand is because I just don't do that
um because it can only lead to
portability problems in some sense uh if
you start relying on stuff like that I
think
um
so what is the so Gareth Luen is saying
that allocating cross boundaries there's
a different reason for it but I'm not
sure he doesn't
actually posted what it is so I'm not
sure what the answer is um what he
wanted me to
say uh so so I don't know if there is a
way he could of course there's a delay
so now he doesn't know that I'm asking
him to post what he wants to say but um
let's
see uh so the internet FTW says from the
system maintains a per process reference
count for each dll yes it does when the
reference count becomes zero the DLS
unloaded from the virtual out of space
the process yes it does the dll uses the
stack of the calling thread and the
virtual address bace of the calling
process yes uh the D allocates memory
from the virtual address bace of the
calling process yes
uh
so but that's what I all just said right
so that sounds like msdn is just saying
what I said is there something that so I
don't know if someone could tell me what
they think is incorrect because I just
want to make sure before we end the
stream that if there is something
incorrect that I could correct it or
Point people to the correct version of
it uh but that sounds exactly
correct
[Music]
so I got
nothing so Gareth
Luen uh you you have a a few more
seconds here to tell me what it is you
think is incorrect um otherwise it will
have to wait I suppose till discussion
on the forums if someone thinks there is
something incorrect about that
explanation um so I will go ahead and
say that now um so if uh we are
basically at the end of the stream but
I'm going to wait a little bit just to
let the questions up catch up there in
case someone wants to type in what they
think was wrong about that explanation
uh
basically if you go to handmad her.org
um and obviously you can pre-order The
Source on here if you'd like to if you'd
like to follow along at home you can get
the source code every night I pushed the
source code uh every night so you can
redownload it and see where we were at
um if you'd like to follow along at home
it makes it a lot easier um but you can
also click on news and forums and that
will get you a little resource site here
it has the schedule for the week
typically posted on there it has an
episode guide that you can use uh to
catch up if you're or or to re-reference
older things it has a coding Resource
page which has ports and stuff like that
that you can go to do as well as other
informational good informational
materials and finally there's a Code
discussion button here uh which is where
you can post stuff like if you think an
explanation was incorrect um or you just
weren't sure about something you can
post on here and other people and me uh
read it and try to answer those
questions to try and help out people who
are trying to learn so that's a good
place to go uh to follow up um so let's
see
here okay
um let's
see so all right Gareth says the mistake
is that using msvcrt.dll won't solve the
cross boundary allocation issue uh so if
you could post a reference to why it
doesn't that would be helpful because it
definitely does uh in practice because I
have worked on projects uh in the past
which rely on that specific thing um if
that makes
sense uh while the dll is loaded into
the same address bace as the application
its own Statics are unique
uh so I don't believe that's actually
true I believe that it depend I believe
that um basically the way that the dll
gets mapped in is Statics aren't all the
same if that makes sense uh they can be
defined as shared or not shared uh and
maybe I don't actually know exactly how
that's implemented under the hood but
I'm pretty sure
msvcrt.dll actually does the right thing
there and will P like uses the same Heap
uh for each instance of the d That's
loaded at least that was the way that it
used to work
um I'm like 99% sure about that uh so
yeah uh but all right so if that's the
only objection you had I'm pretty sure
that's not actually true uh so we should
but we can pick that up on the forums
now that I know what the thing is
because that's a pretty small minor
thing uh so let's go ahead and pick that
up on the forums and we can see which
which uh which one is correct but other
than that we are now overtime by 15
minutes so I apologize for the slightly
long stream I just wanted to make sure
that was on there um thank you every
everyone for joining us I hope you
enjoyed this little sort of uh fun uh
dive into how to make C uh be editable
at runtime tomorrow we're going to do
the super cool thing of making it super
easy to edit at runtime getting rid of
sort of the some of the hacky things we
did just to get it working today uh and
so after that we should be in a point
where we can just literally leave the
code up and running the whole time if we
wanted to I don't know if we should or
not but we could from now on um to for
the most part except for a certain
circumstances well we'll have to kind of
do some reloading but we'll do some
other cool stuff tomorrow much like we
did today I hope you enjoyed it uh and I
will see you tomorrow uh at 8:00 P.M
Pacific Standard time when we will
continue uh doing some some fun win32
stuff all right thanks everyone for
joining me and I will see you tomorrow